Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
He didn't come.
You mean Noble Prince Guo?
I'm such a fool.
Why would a prince come here on such a rainy day?
He was joking,
but I took it seriously.
He might have been planning to come,
but the rain made it inconvenient for him.
We should go, My Lady.
Don't get wet.
Let's go.
How is everything in the harem?
Everything's all right.
That's good.
I am too old to take care of the palace.
You're in charge of the harem.
- Put your heart in it.
- I will.
Your Majesty, I came here already.
There was no one here.
It's understandable not to come on such a bad day.
Nothing is as important as Your Majesty's health.
Please go take shelter from the wind and rain.
Your Majesty has been coughing for sleeping late recently.
I'll be punished if Your Majesty catches a cold.
Your Majesty, please go.
"Over the majestic mountain rises a moon so tiny."
"The moon so tiny is silvery and shiny."
"I pine for the man traveling distantly."
"Each day apart makes my heart sink heavy."
What song are you playing?
Nothing.
The zither plays out the performer's heart.
My Lady, you have something on your mind.
He is a prince, and you are a concubine.
If you'll pardon my saying so, you shouldn't have gone today.
I know.
I know that I'm just an Attendant in seclusion.
Even if I have never seen His Majesty,
I will not have anything to do with Noble Prince Guo.
You are a concubine of His Majesty
wile he is a brother of his.
You won't be able to get away when rumors fly.
I know.
Sourire.
The rain just stopped.
I hope you walked safe on the slippery road.
I don't need to attend to His Majesty when he's sick.
What else can I do if I don't come here?
Meizhuang is there.
She must be having trouble with Consort Fleur.
Have a cup of tea.
It is strange that His Majesty fell ill.
Why would he get a cold on a warm day?
Everyone feels under the weather sometimes.
The medicine is ready for Your Majesty.
Bring it to me.
Let me help Your Majesty with it.
You've been here the whole night.
You should go get some rest.
I can't put my mind at ease
when the other concubines are taking care of you.
Meizhuang is reliable.
She is, but she is a new concubine.
She's inexperienced in this.
My Lady, Lunar is here.
Peace to Attendant Sourire.
Lady Shen received textiles for the spring.
Please go take your pick.
Why's she available today?
I thought she was taking care of His Majesty.
Is His Majesty all right now?
Yes, Lady Shen didn't go since the night before last.
I regret that I am missing the spring in my garden.
But that is the reason Your Majesty caught a cold.
The Empress Dowager mentioned the spring flowers.
I was hoping to pick some flowers for her in the garden,
only to find myself caught in the rain.
I know that Your Majesty was being a filial son,
but they say that the wicked flowers captured your heart.
Not as wicked as the green-eyed monster.
You talk much more than your read.
You've been tired lately.
Go have a good rest.
The medicine will be ready soon.
You can start working after you've had the medicine.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
We're going out for a walk.
Wait, I need to dress down.
It's her again.
Who is on the swing?
You should come over to greet My Lady.
Hey, you! Come here!
My Lady is Attendant Sourire in the Palace of Pear Jade.
She doesn't dress like an Attendant.
Is there an Attendant Sourire?
I've never heard of you.
My Lady, there is an Attendant in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
But she's been in a quarantine.
Greetings, Attendant Sourire.
I'm Companion Yu.
Greetings.
You seem to be enjoying your walk out here.
Not as often as you do.
I've been busy serving His Majesty.
But there's something I need to tell you.
Stay in your palace while you are sick.
Don't spread your bad luck in the palace.
Thank you for your reminder.
But there's something I need to tell you as well.
Huh? I would very much like to hear it.
His Majesty likes well-mannered concubines.
But you did not greet me properly when you saw me.
You must be unfamiliar with the etiquette in the palace.
How about my maid show you the proper way to greet me?
You can watch and learn.
My Lady,
Peace to Attendant Sourire.
I am Companion Yu.
I heard that Companion Yu is a fast learner.
I believe you are able to do it properly this time.
You are just an invisible Attendant.
You want me to greet you like that?
How dare you?
My Lady, Attendant Sourire does rank above you ...
Who do you work for?
Do you really think that your status
in the palace is determined by your rank?
You rank higher if His Majesty likes you.
Otherwise, your rank means nothing.
And for your information, you are just one rank above me.
How dare you tell me what to do?
What if I tell you what to do?
What if I make you bow to Attendant Sourire.
Peace to Your Majesty.
What brought Your Majesty here?
And what brought you here?
I heard that Your Majesty has been coming here a lot.
I thought the garden must be beautiful,
so I came here for a walk.
You're not being honest.
I was simply hoping to keep Your Majesty company.
How did you know my whereabouts?
My Lady ... My Lady ...
Peace and Grace to Your Majesty.
I didn't mean to stand you up that day.
I kept thinking about you when I was ill.
Did you come here and wait afterwards?
Rise.
Hold on to your mistress.
She's fragile.
My Lady.
You didn't learn your lesson!
It seems that the punishment
by the Empress Dowager was too lenient.
Your Majesty, I admit my fault.
I was out of my mind to offend Attendant Sourire.
I will ... I will beg Attendant Sourire for her forgiveness.
Please allow me another chance!
I dare not beg for your forgiveness of my appalling offence.
I hope to ask for leniency as we both are serving His Majesty.
"A fault confessed is half redressed."
Your Majesty, I believe Companion Yu is truly sorry.
I hope Your Majesty can forgive her.
I shall not make Attendant Sourire lose face
since she spoke up for you.
But I can't forgive a second-time offender.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Yu is demoted to Escort.
She will move out of the Palace of Purity
into a place out of sight.
Your Majesty.
You were saying that Attendant was just one rank above you.
I hereby upgrade her to Noble Lady.
Your Majesty, it is inappropriate to upgrade
Attendant Sourire before she serves you.
Now you do your job by telling me how to do my job?
I dare not. I will announce your edict right away.
There she stands overjoyed,
not remembering to say thank you.
I made no contribution to state affairs or family expansion.
I do not deserve the heavenly grace.
You do when I say so.
Rise.
Don't tire yourself out by kneeling.
Escort Yu, please take your leave.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Are you scared?
Got sweaty hands and cold feet?
You are the Emperor.
You weren't afraid of me.
I didn't know you are the Emperor.
Your Majesty inspires awe in my humble being.
Awe induces inhibition,
and that will turn us into monarch and subject.
I didn't mean to stand you up that day.
I was just a few steps away from the garden
when the Empress Dowager summoned me.
I hurried to the garden only to find my lady gone.
I had a cold for days.
Has Your Majesty been feeling better?
I am right here, as right as rain.
It was silly of me.
It was because you care.
With hindsight, you wouldn't be able to go out
in the heavy rain while you were sick.
In fact, I came to the garden that day.
For real?
Were you caught in the rain?
Did that affect your recovery?
I thank Your Majesty.
I am right here, as right as rain.
That's good.
I was asking because you've been sick since you moved in.
But why would Your Majesty deceive me?
I wouldn't.
I was just hoping that you would not be
afraid, obedient, or fawning because of who I am.
I hope I will not end up alone in the palace,
where I have no one to talk my heart to.
I dare not see myself as Your Majesty's confidante.
I appreciate you for who you are.
I wouldn't be take our rendezvous so seriously
were you like the other concubines.
I feel so silly for not discovering your identity.
How would you know when I deliberately hide from you.
Prince XVII is bitter about this, however.
He's been confined in my palace lately.
You planned it thoughtfully. I wouldn't know.
You hand is cold.
Is it because of the windy day?
I'm all right.
You've been here for quite a while.
I'll walk you back.
No, I'll carry you back instead, not to make you tired.
I dare not.
Why not?
They would talk about it.
Let them talk about it.
I must take care of my lady.
Peace to Your Majesty. Peace to Lady Sourire.
You guys are in the know.
The Palace of Pearl Jade is honored
by Your Majesty's grace to My Lady.
We are deeply grateful.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You are smart and articulate. What's your name?
My name is Vermilion. I'm the dowry maid of My Lady.
You attract like-minded servants.
I thank Your Majesty.
My arms hut.
Is Your Majesty calling me heavy?
Not at all, I was trying to make you comfortable,
but not too comfortable to make you fall.
It wasn't easy to strike a balance.
I feel embarrassed.
Are all the servants here?
My palace was overstaffed for a patient like me.
But this is unacceptable.
Who are the head eunuch and head maid?
Your Majesty, I am the head maid.
My name is Cui Jinxi.
There is currently no head eunuch.
The former head eunuch Kang Luhai was sent to work
for Concubine Beauté two months ago.
That's all right.
But you need a head eunuch in your palace.
I will ask the Household Department
to select a few candidates for you.
You will make the final call.
I thank Your Majesty.
That sounds like a lot of trouble.
I would like to have Xiao-Yunzi as my head eunuch.
I thank Your Majesty.
I thank My Lady.
I will do everything I can to serve My Lady.
Yes, as you wish.
The other eunuchs don't know you as well.
Lady Sourire appreciates your work.
I'm counting on you.
Yes, Your Majesty.
You will need more servants as a Noble Lady.
The Household Department will arrange for you.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Zhang Tingyu requests to see you.
For sure.
You can have a good rest now.
I'll see you in two days.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
You know my rules.
I know that Your Majesty wouldn't like to be disturbed
(peace)
when you are practicing calligraphy.
I just wanted to inform you that
Companion Yu was demoted to Escort.
By His Majesty?
Exactly.
That happened sooner than I expected.
Make sure that she's behaving herself.
Yu is too shallow to serve His Majesty.
And she went out of her mind.
What happened?
She offended Lady Sourire in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
That was fast.
Is His Majesty quite fond of her?
It seems so. But it's against the rules to upgrade
a concubine before she serves His Majesty.
The rules were made by the emperors,
so can they be made by the emperor.
"A dragon does not belong to the pond."
It's just a matter of time for her.
- Goodbye, Mr Lu.
- Thank you for coming.
Peace to Lady Sourire. His Majesty
dispatched gifts for you as soon as he got back.
Thank you for bringing them.
It is my pleasure to send you the gifts.
Here are a pair of gold sachets,
a pair of blue cloisonné bracelets,
a pair of orchid gold hairpins,
a pair of jade Ruyi, a pearl curtain,
sixteen pieces of satin in various colors,
and a special gift from His Majesty.
Please have a look, My Lady.
I thank His Majesty.
His Majesty wishes the flute will
jazz up your life as you make a recovery.
I hope to trouble you to thank His Majesty for me
because of my health conditions.
My pleasure.
For you to have undisturbed rest,
His Majesty allows you to decline visitors
other than himself and the doctors.
I hope Madam Cui can see to it.
Certainly, it was very considerate of His Majesty.
Allow me to take my leave.
Our storeroom has been filled with gifts.
- Huan.
- Meizhuang.
This day has finally come.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
You shouldn't ... We are sisters.
Meizhuang was thrilled with your good news
and rushed me all the way here.
But I have to stay clear-headed not to break any rules.
That's true, let's go inside.
Sure.
You guys don't need to follow.
How did you rise to Lady Sourire without a sound?
I did not even have the faintest clue.
I never mean to hide from you.
I met His Majesty accidentally in the garden.
"A quiet bird amazes the world when she sings."
That is the story of your life.
I thought it was rumor when my maids told me about it.
We were convinced when Mr Su came to announce the edict.
We hurried here without a moment's delay.
But countless pairs of eyes will be watching you from now.
- You have to be careful.
- I will.
His Majesty made an exception to your upgrade.
You don't need to worry as he likes you so much.
It does worry me to be the exception.
There's not much they can do
while you are His Majesty's new favorite.
Yu was punished by His Majesty for offending you.
That is a great example for everyone.
She was at fault, but I'm afraid
the same would happen to me one day.
That could make my entire family suffer.
There's no escape when you are front and center.
But that is better than taking the back seat.
The only concern you should have is to
regain your health and live your life as a Noble Lady.
Lingrong is right.
We won't be defeated as we join our hands.
What the heck is this?
Why wasn't it cleaned?
My Lady, you are not living in the Palace of Purity any more.
You would have been sent to the Cold Palace
without His Majesty's liking for you.
You wouldn't have your own palace and maid there.
My Lady, you can clean up by yourself and deal with it.
Sir, please let me see His Majesty.
His Majesty will forgive me.
I'm flattered.
But I work for Mr Xia [Xiao-Xiazi]
Since you despise us for being eunuchs,
we are unworthy to serve you.
Take it easy, My Lady.
How dare you! (X4)
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
I brought the stipend for Your Highness's palace.
It looks more than what we had last month.
Our department is graced by Your Highness.
We would like to offer Your Highness extras.
You have a grateful heart.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Now that His Majesty has a new Noble Lady,
the Household Department must be busy with her.
Thank you, we are doing okay.
We won't fuss over a Noble Lady.
Lady Sourire must have been getting trouble from
your department before she rose from obscurity.
But now she's front and center.
You can't turn a blind eye to her any more.
There's nothing I can do if she whispers in His Majesty's ear.
Please advise me what to do.
What can I say?
Give her the best service you can offer.
My Lady, Consort Fleur had desserts sent to you.
Her Highness's palace makes better desserts than the Imperial Kitchen.
They are a luxury in the palace.
You can go now.
The dessert looks ten times nicer than what we have.
Enjoy, My Lady.
It reminds me how Consort Fleur punished Xia with the Scarlet Red.
Jinxi, I'm living on my nerves.
Fear is not enough for dealing with
the unpredictable life in the harem.
The only thing you know for sure
is that you have to hold a place in His Majesty's heart.
Too high a place is frowned upon.
Too low a place is trodden upon.
My Lady, you must be aware that
not for a day can you stay away from the rivalries.
When you make friends with Lady Shen and Companion An,
you three become the target of many.
Meizhuang and I grew up together.
We are of one heart and one mind.
I didn't mean that friends are a bad thing.
Your life in the harem is intertwined with
your family at the imperial court.
Consort Fleur is the perfect example of
how the harem is connected the the state affairs.
I simply wish my family can have a peaceful life,
and that His Majesty have an honest heart for me.
Good for you, My Lady.
My Lady, you are different from the ordinary girls as a concubine.
You don't always have control over your life.
Fortunately, His Majesty is very fond of you.
I was going to make three wishes in the Garden of Leaning Plums.
But I wasn't able to say the last one.
I'm all ears.
My third wish is to be loved wholeheartedly.
But the man I love happens to be
the last person to love with his whole heart.
You can wish for an earnest heart
instead of a whole heart.
My Lady, you have recovered in general.
But I can still explain to His Majesty that
you are not in a position to serve him overnight.
We have long been slowing down my recovery.
If His Majesty sends other doctors to make a diagnosis,
will they be able to find out?
What will happen if they find out?
We had a choice last time.
This time, I have to make a full recovery behind closed doors.
We have no option.
Yes, My Lady.
I would be walking on thin ice without your help.
I will always keep my promise.
Thank you.
Please restore me to health,
but not so fast.
A month will be the best.
I will reduce the dosage and add tonic herbs.
Thank you, Mr Wen.
Goodbye, Mr Wen.
Peace to My Lady.
We selected the best maids and eunuchs to serve you, My Lady.
Please rise.
I put my trust in you, Mr Huang.
I'll send for you if they ever let me down.
Jinxi, help them orient themselves.
Follow me.
I beg your forgiveness of my negligence.
I've been busy lately so I asked Xiao-Luzi
to take care of the maintenance request from your palace.
But this bastard dared to forget about it.
He's here to take the punishment.
We dare not punish your staff, Mr Huang.
They will talk about us behind our back.
Vermilion, is that how you should talk?
My apologies. It was all my fault that my staff were ill-disciplined.
Don't worry, sir.
The Household Department is taking care of the entire palace.
It's understandable to make an oversight.
Thank you so much for your understanding.
We will do better than out best to serve you in the future.
We brought you a new table.
I hope you can pardon its shabbiness.
Thank you for remembering.
Xiao-Yunzi, we'll keep it.
I shall take my leave if you do not have other requests.
Take care, sir.
Why were you so impertinent?
Huang Guiquan is trying to have it both ways.
He sent a scapegoat to butter you up.
You could keep that to yourself and keep an eye out for him.
They will call us arrogant if you offend him openly.
Uh, I'm sorry.
I know you were doing it for me.
But we are not fighting a battle of the tongue.
Huang Guiquan is just one of the many snobs in the palace.
I'm sorry, My Lady.
It's all right.
Now he's alarmed.
Tell the servants not to talk about it.
My Lady, Huang Guiquan is a relative of Consort Fleur.
I know. I 'll keep Jinxi and Xiao-Yunzi watching the newcomers.
They will only do the menial jobs.
You guys will keep doing my personal tasks.
Yes, My Lady.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
His Majesty will be here after lunch.
Please get prepared.
Thank you, sir.
Take your time to get changed.
My Lady, you can wear a bright-colored dress for His Majesty.
Why? This looks fine.
But it's a bit too simple.
Let's keep it homey.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
It's windy outside. Let's go in quickly.
"A lotus surfaced from the water,
Her beauty naturally unadorned.”
Lady Sourire is one of a kind.
Because Your Majesty appreciates my plainness.
Your maids dress as elegantly as you.
It's a refreshing sight to see.
Jade is my dowry maid.
A Jade in jade.
Jade.
Let's stay outside.
His Majesty might like to have fewer followers.
Sure.
While some other maids are in jade,
you were the only one noticed by His Majesty.
I thought His Majesty would notice Vermilion first for her red dress.
But you look like My Lady and Vermilion doesn't.
That's why you caught His Majesty's attention.
For real?
Your Majesty, I made tea for you.
I hope you will like it.
I would like anything you do for me.
Smells great!
It smells fresh and goes deep into my lungs.
It's the winter tea from Yuezhou.
I can recognize the taste of plum flowers and pine leaves.
What else did you put in it?
Your Majesty is a tea expert.
The name of the tea is "the three friends in winter".
It's made of plum flowers, pine leaves, and chrysanthemums.
The water is the dew drops collected from the lotus leaves.
"Tea clears a foggy mind."
I learned that is true today.
I'm flattered.
I received two jars of the tea last year.
I kept one under the pear tree in the yard.
We opened it two days ago.
How do you like living in this palace?
It's quite a remote palace.
Thank Your Majesty for asking.
I like living here. It's quiet and peaceful.
But it's a bit far from the Palace of Mental Cultivation.
But I'm always willing to go the extra mile.
As long as our hearts are close.
Yes, our hearts are close.
You look much healthier.
You'll be fully recovered soon.
It wouldn't have take so long.
I was particularly frail.
Blessed with Your Majesty's care and support,
I will get better sooner.
I can't take my eyes away from you when you're shy.
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.